[SPEAKER_02]: What does it mean to endure things rightly?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it just about patience and gritting one's teeth within the framework of the precepts, or is there more to it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's how it starts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you certainly shouldn't be trying to...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're just starting out, you haven't been keeping the precepts, you don't really have anything to endure except the discomfort of not breaking the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fundamentally, it is more than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not just waiting, as if simply not doing certain things externally is going to tame your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It may not even be uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will get used to it pretty soon.
[SPEAKER_01]: As most monks do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it doesn't even mean that they're practicing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's... What you have to endure is much more than just random pains as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you're not just seeking out things to to make yourself experience pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's when the mind craves for something and you don't provide it,
[SPEAKER_01]: When pain comes up, that's what you endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not even about the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not even that the pain is good or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It simply is a symptom of the fact that you're not giving in to something unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you, by enduring the pain, like, unless you can endure the pain, you will cease to restrain that unwholesome thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's really what the emphasis should be in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I restraining the unwholesome intention that arose, whether or not it's painful?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if it's painful, I endure it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But sometimes, it may not even be painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: In fact, eventually, it would be pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then, the mind starts to understand that not going for those things is actually the better alternative.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in terms of, like, how do you do that then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, how do you know that you're actually restraining an unwholesome intention?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, precisely by not putting the emphasis on whether it's painful or pleasant to... like, whether the situation is painful or pleasant is not to measure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It could be extremely painful to not do something and then it's actually bad, like you're actually going the wrong way by avoiding that thing, like all the self-mortification practices that you would read about in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because those things are imposed independently of discerning the mind's craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just abstractly reasoned as, oh, well, if I renounce more things, then I am closer to freedom from attachments or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what you want to see is, what are the things that my mind is actually leaning towards?
[SPEAKER_01]: Meaning, kind of the things that I kind of find myself being being pushed
[SPEAKER_01]: To engage in these things, whether I like it or not, and then I can, you know, secondarily say yes or say no.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, fundamentally, that impulse was there first.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, those are the things you want to start investigating and seeing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, and you will see, naturally, when you don't follow those impulses that came on their own, but you actually discern them,
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then, that's the only way that you will be restraining them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, you're just doing random observances externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you actually see those impulses.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't give in to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, that discomfort is going to come up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Strongly or weakly, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: What matters is, you didn't give in.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_02]: That happens with the precepts, obviously.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just like...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a bit simpler in the sense that you don't really have to question your intentions as much, especially in the beginning, because it's pretty clear what you shouldn't do.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for somebody who's who's not used to even that, then it's gonna... just that blind keeping the precepts is already gonna involve restraining their intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: But at some point, you're not even gonna have intentions to break the precepts, but you're gonna have other intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Still based on craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you're not making effort to discern them, then nothing is going to show you that they're unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not even that you're going to be feeding this massive dukkha on account of them that would show you that there's a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's when you would have to start seeing, like, well, regardless of whether it's externally prohibited or regardless of even whether it feels painful when I engage in it, I have to start putting first the fact that, well, there was an impulse there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the going along with those impulses, in and of itself, keeps you within saṃsāra, because it means, you know, you could have survived that one episode, could have been fine, nothing bad happened, but you are training your mind, you're training yourself, so that when things come up painful or pleasant, you have to act.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's going to be a matter of time until that...
[SPEAKER_01]: In fact, well, the mere... if you were to, let's say, see in hindsight, the mere fact of needing to act, even if there are absolutely no negative consequences on account of it externally, the mere fact of needing to act, that impulse, is already painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's already a burden that you're carrying.
[SPEAKER_01]: But obviously, you've been carrying that forever, so you don't realize it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's an issue, whatever kind of pressure it is, to still be giving into it, because you're you're training that habit.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that it doesn't seem like an issue is actually exactly how it goes on indefinitely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody just wakes up and abandons existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just get caught up in it one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, like, the enduring things rightly is less about, let's say, finding the right method or technique or way of enduring.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's more the discernment and clarity towards what I'm actually enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, but even then, like, it's... again, the point is not what... the point is not the enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the enduring is a side effect of not giving in to something unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's important because if you put first the enduring,
[SPEAKER_01]: You might ignore that that very effort that you're putting into endure this is, let's say, a type of restlessness, like subjecting yourself to painful circumstances out of some impatient attitudes towards the practice, like you want to speed it up or something, and then you go and start fasting or whatever out of that intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not that it's
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not inherently bad to experience difficulties, and you should always try to go the comfortable route.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is always, why were you going towards that?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, then you would be overlooking what actually matters, if you just think that enduring discomfort is inherently part of the training.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, enduring discomfort is what goes hand in hand
[SPEAKER_01]: With not giving in to unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't mean that whenever you're enduring discomfort, you're actually not giving into something unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: In fact, you could even be enduring discomfort on account of, like, I don't know, having given into sensual things, like enduring the discomfort of a marriage or having kids.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it will feel... there will always be discomfort if I restrain myself from giving in to the impulses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, it doesn't have to be super coarse and like you're falling apart or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's just... there's a uneasiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it would have felt easier to just go with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's pretty much the definition of what an impulse is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there would be the difference as well between... like, wrongly enduring would be still doing the endurance as a form of activity, whereas rightly enduring is, like you said, the result of discerning and having clarity about, fundamentally, what's wholesome, what's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: It becomes a duty you take up, which is blinding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I do this because it is good by itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if it stops being unpleasant, then you feel like, okay, so what do I do now?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's like... that wasn't the point.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you mentioned speeding up the practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Are there any ways or legitimate, yeah, reasons, I guess, for actually speeding up the practice?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or what would be a way to speed up the practice, if there is a way?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it can never be anything you do blindly, that's for sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it can never be just a technique or method that you do and you just apply it verbatim and then that makes it work by itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, like, you follow this procedure and the product is going to be assembled and ready just because you follow the procedure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It never works that way, because the entire training, the... well, suffering as well, is all based on your intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you cannot fix the issue without actually addressing the root cause.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, the way to speed up the practice, actually,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, look for what are the things that you are not actually restraining, that are impulses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, quite often, actually, you would naturally gravitate to picking up these random observances.
[SPEAKER_01]: As like, okay, well, if I stop eating with a spoon, I will... because you need... that's more uncomfortable and surely, like, that's gonna...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's preferable to eat with a spoon versus not eating with a spoon.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's preferable to wear clothes rather than being naked.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's preferable to eat normal food versus just eating leaves.
[SPEAKER_01]: Therefore, surely, I am giving up craving because I am going for this more difficult thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But was there an impulse there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that you were actually, like, were you obsessed about wearing clothes and eating with a spoon?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or do you just assume that because it's more difficult, it's going to be training your mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, ironically, simply because you have that view, you have impulses that you will completely overlook and give in to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's what the Buddha and the suttas... you would see these criticisms of these ascetics back in the day, that they would be doing all these inspiring ascetic practices,
[SPEAKER_01]: But then they would, like, when whenever a monk would arrive, like a Buddhist monk, to see them, it would be like just absolutely making a racket, arguing about their views, you know, like just behaving like just unrestrained, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: And obviously, it doesn't have to be that way in order to still, you know, it could be small things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That nobody would blame you for, externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody would think, oh, look, he's greedy, or he's averse.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were honest, you would say, oh, yeah, I do have an impulse for this, that I'm not really able to... Like, if I didn't give in to it, I would be subject to rebellion from my own mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, those are the things that you have to... it really comes down to honesty, to recognizing those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, that's how you will speed up your practice, like not making exceptions on that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, yeah, almost like very rarely would it actually be something very straightforward, where you could just decide, oh, I'm not going to do X and that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's far more subtle than that most of the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's a specific kind of habits and avenues of sort of finding safety that you might have, making things the way you prefer.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the problem is like, if you don't have enough honesty, you won't even see them, because it's just like... it just goes through.
[SPEAKER_01]: Automatically accepted.
[SPEAKER_02]: And they're probably not too big of a deal as well, that people you would live with would point it out to you, and would say, well, it's not okay to behave like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's not even necessarily the same thing all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like every single day I'm doing it, and like, it's just obvious.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you have to learn to pick up the signs of your mind, as Siddha described.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the same way as the the king doesn't have the same preferences from day to day,
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't even have the same impulses from day to day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Initially, you will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sexuality and these very coarse things, you can just pinpoint them and be sure, like, okay, I'm still struggling with this, but eventually, it's going to be kind of so...
[SPEAKER_01]: Indirect.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, not necessarily like hidden, but just personal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, personal or kind of circumstantial as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like it's not even going to come up every day.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were honest, you would know in this specific scenario, which I may never have experienced before, this way of acting is going along with the impulses.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it would be... like, obviously, speeding up the practice usually comes along with, okay, I'm going to pile these additional activities, additional observances on top of each other.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, restraining that as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's that's going to be part of speeding up your practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, not acting out of... See, that's a great example, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: These these restless impulses that you would have to to just pile up more things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if, again, it feels completely justified.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even mentally contemplating.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, just adding, like, oh, I've spent three hours every day contemplating such and such.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, I read in the suttas that this leads to arhantship.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I'm just gonna... And then, yeah, sure, somebody might have dedicated themselves to contemplating that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But are you doing it out of an impulse?
[SPEAKER_01]: In which case, you certainly are not contemplating whatever it is that was actually being referred to there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because whatever it is that is actually wholesome, is along the lines of subduing impulses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's also why the practice really begins with the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when you have this reference point to know, oh, this is actually an impulse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you will be able to include craving, actually, rather than just kind of blindly accepting it, when it camouflages itself into these kind of supposed wholesome things.
[SPEAKER_02]: It would be like a practical way of going about it, given that you are in an environment that's, you know...
[SPEAKER_02]: Where there isn't any kind of course obstructions that you... You have certain activities that are just on a day-to-day basis you need to do to maintain the place, to maintain yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, you need to eat, you need to clean a few things, probably even as a lay person, if you kind of live on your own or family.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you have certain activities throughout the day that are necessary in a way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, then, there might be days, it's raining, you cannot clean, and then you will actually might notice, oh, actually, there's this restlessness, and then did the cleaning all.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, let's say, you have these basic activities.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, exactly, but that doesn't mean, that doesn't mean that you were always cleaning out of that restlessness.
[SPEAKER_01]: It depends.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, see, that's what I meant just now with, like, situation just come up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it doesn't necessarily have to have any connection with anything that happened before.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, it could be that you just, right now, have an impulse to get rid of that lack of activity somehow.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you need to see it there and then, as like, okay, this impulse has arisen now, rather than sort of solidify it too much into like, okay, so I'm just like doing too much, so let me take on an observance of reducing my activities and just doing less.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even if, sometimes, you were doing the cleaning out of restlessness, the fact that you just imposed it in that blanket way means you don't know what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, some other impulse is going to come up and you're not going to see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just moving from one thing to the other, basically, like a... kind of like a... like a shadow, like, you know, wherever you cast the light, now the shadow is elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't have to be that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like it's inherently kind of arcane and has so many moving parts that it's just... that's why it's so hard to succeed in training your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that kind of tendency to prioritize things that are secondary and not want to look at the often very simple fact that, yes, there is an impulse here.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you kind of have a tendency to just do anything other than sort of stay with that ambiguous level of, oh, I see that there's just this pressure towards this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, not even necessarily towards a specific thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just arose that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it kind of looks for gratification here and there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And just seeing that as the issue, like seeing, acting out of that as the issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not, oh, but how many times a day I end up cleaning, or how many hours a day I spend cleaning.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's much easier to just, kind of, because then you can, you can...
[SPEAKER_01]: Get a lot more certainty and say, okay, so now, from now onwards, if I just limit my cleaning to one hour a day, I'll be fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then, you won't have to think about it next time.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't have to see what impulse is there next time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's kind of like, everybody has that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you already want to know what you're going to do ahead.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it just doesn't work that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the the impulses, the direction of the impulses, is going to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like you have a fog, such that you can only see ahead of you, like, one meter.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you have to accept that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, whatever map do you think you have of what's gonna come after, it's not... it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to make decisions based on, like, what's right ahead of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like your sense of urgency is getting ignored.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's a misdirected sense of urgency.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because the sense of urgency leads to, like, effort, faith, all of those are factors of awakening or things that lead to awakening if you have the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you know what it is that you have to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, sense of urgency can be...
[SPEAKER_01]: Imagine, like, how many wrong views you could pick up with a sense of urgency.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's good to have a sense of urgency and you need to have it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, you won't be going against the grain, as the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it needs to be informed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It needs to be redirected.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like, yeah, if I feel impatient and I feel like I'm not going fast enough with my practice, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't mean you need to kind of, like, deny it and say, nah, you know, it's good enough or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, no, maybe you are lacking in some respects, but you have to keep in mind, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't even necessarily... like, you're not gonna get anything of value by analyzing things in this kind of abstract way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, kind of, as if there is some specific action that I just have to stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's some specific behavior that I just have to say no to forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Except the precepts, of course, but we're assuming that that's covered.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you have to be ready that, no, it's really just I have to be vigilant for completely new things that I've never encountered before.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's going to be more accurate than thinking like, oh, it's just these
[SPEAKER_01]: I can just make a determination and then assume that everything that comes after is going to be covered.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're like... you're facing each day and you're making... you're making your decisions based on what impulses have I... am I discerning right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is the sense of urgency
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's problematic because it comes with a pressure that you can't endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the sense of urgency that's problematic.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you need to have it in order to practice, even the craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as I said, craving is overcome by means of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is going to be a pressure behind it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, like I said, it matters what you do on account of that pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not all on the same level.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can have a sense of urgency and you can decide to do 1000 prostrations to diminish your conceit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, that's a very coarse example, obviously, but just to illustrate the principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, you can look more closely at when you speak, why are you speaking?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, what are your motivations for speech?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like, oh, I should speak less, automatically, and I should just take a vow of silence.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pressure of the sense of urgency, is that different from, you know, you're just taking on the precepts and now you're calming down within, you know, that pressure that you get when you first take on the precepts and it's like... Obviously, then you just want to put out the fire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the sense of urgency is what would have led you to take on the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you didn't feel like you were
[SPEAKER_01]: Under some kind of threat, you wouldn't have done such an unnatural thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which was certainly, at least in the beginning, it wasn't natural.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not even like... For example, see, you could even say, oh, okay, so I shouldn't have a sense of urgency.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which, again, it's like you remove or you try to remove
[SPEAKER_01]: The opportunity for problems to arise, rather than just removing the problems, which is always going to fail, because as long as you exist, there is going to be the opportunity for problems, for defilements to arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sense of urgency isn't the issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's obviously something that can result in kind of misdirections, but it's not the issue in and of itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically the fact that when you have the sense of urgency, it comes up.
[SPEAKER_01]: You let it overly proliferate into just a blind restlessness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as a... as a... just a call to action.
[SPEAKER_01]: It could very well be, oh, actually, I should restrain my restlessness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will be doing that out of a sense of urgency.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could actually realize, okay, I need to practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not doing enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then realize, oh, actually, that's true.
[SPEAKER_01]: I haven't been doing enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: But right now, I have this this pressure to, I don't know,
[SPEAKER_01]: Just start saying no to something.
[SPEAKER_01]: That I'm... that is not even always unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: But like, I just feel that if I just remove this, I'll be kind of somehow getting ahead.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize, well, but this is clearly coming out of that impulse.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I have a sense of urgency that I should be freeing myself from craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's right there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you will need the sense of urgency to stick to that, because it's not going to happen automatically.
[SPEAKER_01]: You let your guard down, and then something else is going to come up, and you will act out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why the whole thing of like, oh, you abstain from these
[SPEAKER_01]: Restless activities, activities based on craving, many times, can sound to people as if, okay, so, that just means you don't do anything, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is, or there's no need for effort.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's all just passive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, I mean, this is to describe it all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will take effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, see, if it was easier to stick to that middle way and neither indulge nor go for these blind observances, then you wouldn't need the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would just be natural for everybody to already be doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you will need effort to pull yourself back from both of those directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And actually, you don't need effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: of that right kind to go for one of the two, because it's what your mind wants anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like as I said, those impulses, you kind of find them there already.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if it feels like effort, like when, let's say, when you really want to do something, when there's a project that you really want to complete,
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you spend days and nights, like, not sleeping or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you might think, okay, yeah, this requires effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, sure, in a worldly sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the effort of the practice, the effort that leads to awakening, is like when it's not actually something that you have an impulse for.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because otherwise, it cannot be nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nibbāna is the cessation of impulses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't arrive at that magically, by giving into impulses.